A Guide to the Peter F. Geithner papers FA1408
Rockefeller Archive Center
Peter F. Geithner papers
1951-2011
Rockefeller Archive Center
Geithner, Peter F.
Ford Foundation
FA1408
55.77 Cubic Feet 123 LTR size Hollinger boxes, 3 Half-LTR size Hollinger boxes, and 18 LGL size Hollinger boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Other Finding Aids
Finding aids concerning Ford Foundation records produced by the office of Peter F. Geithner when Geithner served as Regional Director of Asia Programs:
FA505 Ford Foundation records, Asia Programs, Regional Director, Office Files of Peter F. Geithner
FA506 Ford Foundation records, Asia Programs, Subject Files of Peter F. Geithner
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by Peter F. Geithner in 2012.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series and seven subseries.
The six series derive from the original systems of arrangement used to organize the collection that were discerned during acquisition, accessioning, and processing. Peter F. Geithner appears to have used several different systems and methods for organizing his personal papers. His movements between different offices and different homes and the large timespan from which the records originate may help illuminate why the papers have various arrangement schemes. Furthermore, a significant amount of material was impacted by mold growth and removed from the collection pending mold remediation. Greater insight into Geithner's organizational systems may be gained if the impacted material is treated and reintegrated into the collection.
The bulk of the collection's content is contained within the first two groupings of material observed within the collection. The first grouping housed the content in a set of boxes labeled alphabetically, A-Z, while the second housed the content in a set of boxes labeled numerically, 1-14D. In regards to the A-Z boxes, the alphabetical arrangement did not reflect the organization of the files within those containers. The 1-14D boxes also did not have a consistent internal organizational structure for the files it held. Both groupings contained records created during Geithner's time at the Ford Foundation as well as from after he retired from Ford. They also both contain professional and personal material, and they overlap in terms of creation dates. Within the finding aid, they are described as Series 1 and 2. Professional and personal files, first and second run.
The other four groupings are smaller and have more clearly defined points of focus. Original box titles, internal arrangement schemes, and varying points of origin helped identify these groupings. They are described in the finding aid as: Series 3. Ford Foundation, Vietnam and China; Series 4. Ford Foundation, Asia-Pacific regional issues; Series 5. Professional and personal files, third run; and Series 6. Ford Foundation, trips, meetings, and conferences. Series 3 was broken into two subseries during processing in order to represent its different topical groupings and Series 5 was broken into five subseries during processing in order to represent its different topical groupings and internal organizational systems.
Original order was maintained as much as possible. Records were only moved in the few instances where reordering would support the original arrangement schemes implemented by Geithner. For instance, an original box of materials titled 14C was moved into the second series in order to maintain the numerical system of arrangement Geithner used for that segment of his materials. Likewise, another box of materials was relocated within the collection in order to reconstitute the subject files grouping found in Series 5.
Although Geithner had created files for the majority of the documents found within the collection, there was a significant amount of loose materials in the original boxes. Files were created during processing in order to organize and properly house those records. Decisions regarding these files were based off of structural indications – uses of rubber bands or binder clips to group together items – as well as by contextual and content-centered relationships between items.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Professional and personal files, first run, 1963-2004
Series 2. Professional and personal files, second run, 1951-2011
Series 3. Ford Foundation, Vietnam and China, 1973-1996
Series 3 Subseries 1. Ford Foundation, Vietnam, 1973-1996
Series 3 Subseries 2. Ford Foundation, China, 1986-1996
Series 4. Ford Foundation, Asia-Pacific regional issues, 1994-1999
Series 5. Professional and personal files, third run, 1982-2005
Series 5. Subseries 1. Philanthropy, 1994-2005
Series 5. Subseries 2. Subject files, 1982-2005
Series 5. Subseries 3. Correspondence with individuals, 1995-2005
Series 5. Subseries 4. Philanthropic organizations and research institutions, 1995-2004
Series 5. Subseries 5. Reports, articles, and publications, 1983-2004
Series 6. Ford Foundation, trips, meetings, and conferences, 1989-1997
Biographical / Historical
Peter Franz Geithner (1932-2016) worked in the field of international philanthropy for more than 40 years. Between 1968 and 1996, he provided leadership for the Ford Foundation's program activities in Asia, becoming Ford's Regional Director of Asia Programs in 1990. After serving at Ford for almost three decades, he retired from the foundation in 1996, but remained active in philanthropic organizations and research institutions for many years after that through advisory positions, consultancy appointments, and memberships on various boards and committees. Geithner was married to Deborah Moore, and together, they had four children: Timothy, Sarah, Jonathan, and David.
Raised in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Geithner attended Northeast High School. He graduated in 1950 and then pursued his undergraduate education at Dartmouth College. Between 1954 and 1958, he served in the U.S. Navy as a naval aviator, and he earned his master's degree from the Johns Hopkins University School of Advanced International Studies in 1959. Prior to his work at the Ford Foundation, Geithner had jobs at Columbia Carbon International in New York City between 1959 and 1962 and the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) in Zimbabwe, Zambia, and Washington D.C. between 1962 and 1968.
Geithner began his career at Ford in 1968 as Assistant/Deputy Director for India, Nepal, and Sri Lanka. The Geithner family moved to New Delhi, India in order for him to take up the post. He held this position until 1973 when he and his family relocated to New York where he became Deputy Head, Office of Asia and Pacific. In 1976, he returned to Asia in order to serve as Ford's Representative for Southeast Asia at the Bangkok, Thailand Office. This position preceded a move back to New York in 1981 when he worked as Program Officer in Charge, Developing Countries Program. He became Ford's first representative for China in 1988 and was stationed at the foundation's new Beijing Office. He finished his career at Ford in New York as Regional Director of Asia Programs.
Following his retirement from the Ford Foundation in 1996, Geithner became Advisor to the Asia Center at Harvard University. He also worked as an advisor for the Japan Center for Global Partnership (CGP) and had a succession of consulting appointments with the Asia Pacific Philanthropy Consortium (APPC), Ford, the Rockefeller Foundation, the Sasakawa Peace Foundation (SPF), and the China Medical Board (CMB). In addition, he served on boards and committees for organizations like the National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (NCUSCR), the Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA), the University of Pennsylvania Center for the Advanced Study of India (CASI), and the Harvard-Yenching Institute (HYI).
Geithner continued to focus on philanthropy and research related to Asia in his post-Ford career. However, he also participated in some philanthropic work related to Africa such as when he assisted the Rockefeller Foundation's Nairobi, Kenya Office.
Geithner's work in philanthropy, international relations, and development intersected with and influenced many important historical events and movements affecting the Asia-Pacific Region such as the strengthening of diplomatic ties between the United States and countries like China and Vietnam, the international response to China following the June Fourth Incident at Tiananmen Square, China's economic development and growing place in world politics, the transfer of Hong Kong back to China, the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis, and the impact of terrorism and the War on Terror on philanthropy and international cooperation.
Scope and Contents
This collection holds the papers of Peter F. Geithner who served as Regional Director of Asia Programs for the Ford Foundation between 1990 and 1996. It contains both professional and personal material, and although it chiefly consists of records created during the course of Geithner's long career in philanthropy, it was maintained by Geithner as an individual person and stored at his home in Orleans, Massachusetts. See the Other Finding Aids note to locate Ford Foundation records created by Geithner during his time as Regional Director of Asia Programs.
The collection consists of six series and seven subseries that correspond to the different organizational systems Geithner employed to arrange his papers. Although the creation dates extend from 1951 when Geithner was a student at Dartmouth College to 2011, the bulk of the collection originates from Geithner's time as Ford's Regional Director of Asia Programs as well as from the period following his retirement from Ford in 1996. Furthermore, there is far more professional material than personal material in the collection. It should be noted that a significant amount of the collection's content was impacted by mold growth and removed for remediation treatment. Files with earlier creation dates and files containing personal material were among those contaminated with mold.
The majority of the collection's material is encompassed by the first two series. These series are based on the two main arrangement schemes Geithner used to organize his records. Documents that were found in a set of boxes labeled alphabetically, A-Z comprise Series 1, and documents that were found in a set of boxes labeled numerically, 1-14D comprise Series 2. The broad scopes of these two series are represented within the titles created for them during processing. These titles are Series 1. Professional and personal files, first run and Series 2. Professional and personal files, second run. Although the later four series in the collection have more clearly defined focuses and/or internal arrangements, more substantial amounts of records on most of the topics, individuals, and organizations represented within those series are likely to be found in Series 1 and 2.
Files that document Geithner's professional activities mostly originate from four sources: 1) His career at Ford; 2) His advisor positions at the Harvard University Asia Center and the Japan Foundation Center for Global Partnership (CGP); 3) His consultancy appointments with Ford, the Asia Pacific Philanthropy Consortium (APPC), the Rockefeller Foundation, the Sasakawa Peace Foundation (SPF), and the China Medical Board (CMB); and 4) His board and committee memberships with organizations like the National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (NCUSCR), the Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA), the University of Pennsylvania Center for the Advanced Study of India (CASI), and the Harvard-Yenching Institute (HYI). Through his work with these organizations and his other professional contacts, he often collaborated with, served, or came into contact with a number of other civil society, research, and international cooperation groups. Some of these organizations include the Japan Center for International Cooperation (JCIE), the Commission on Human Security (CHS), the Asia Society, the Asia Foundation, the Aspen Institute, the Harvard University Ash Center for Democratic Governance and Innovation, the Council on Foundations, the American Indian Foundation (AIF), the City University of New York (CUNY) Center for Philanthropy and Civil Society, and the Asia Development Research Forum (ADRF).
Personal materials within the collection chiefly consist of Geithner's correspondence with family members and friends as well as a few photographs. Some celebrations and family vacation plans are documented within the files containing personal items.
The most prevalent material formats found in the collection are correspondence, reports, drafts, notes, memos, conference proceedings, agendas, schedules, pamphlets, invoices and receipts, newspaper clippings, cards, maps, and publications. Geithner also created specific files to document his business trips, and they all include copies of the travel reports he would write to log his activities. Additionally, there are several photographs and digital media items in the collection.
AIDS (Disease) -- Prevention; AIDS (Disease) -- Vietnam; Africa; Agricultural development projects; Asia; Asia -- Study and teaching; Bangladesh; Biodiversity conservation; Biotechnology; Cambodia; Censorship; China; China--Foreign relations; China -- Politics and government; Cultural pluralism; Economic assistance; Economic development; Economic development -- China; Economic development -- Research; Economic development -- Vietnam; Economic policy; Educational exchanges; Energy policy; Environmental protection; Environmental protection -- Research; Financial crises; Financial institutions, International; Ford Foundation; Globalization; Hong Kong (China); Human rights; India; Indonesia; Intellectual freedom; International finance; International relations; Investments; Japan; Kenya; Korea; Law -- Study and teaching; Minorities -- Civil rights; Multiculturalism; Nonprofit organizations; Pacific Area; Pakistan; Philippines; Political persecution; Portfolio management; Power resources -- Research; Public health; Regionalism; Rockefeller Foundation; Rule of law; Security, International; Social responsibility of business; South Asia; SouthEast Asia; Students -- Asia -- Political activity; Sustainable development; Taiwan; Thailand; United States -- Foreign economic relations; United States -- Foreign relations -- China; Vietnam; Vietnam --Foreign relations; Women's rights
- Professional and personal files, first run, 1963-2004; 1; 23.73 Cubic Feet About 57 LTR size Hollinger boxes, 1 Half-LTR size Hollinger box, and 4 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the segment of Peter F. Geithner's professional and personal files that was originally organized in boxes labeled A-Z.
  - Columbia University Seminars on Southeast Asia, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA) Semi-Annual Meeting of Trustees, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA) Semi-Annual Meeting of Trustees, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Toyota Foundation 20th Anniversary Symposia, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Ford Foundation Education and Culture Program World Wide Workshop, Mali and Senegal, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Asia Society/Institute for National Policy Research (INPR) - Taiwan Study Mission, 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Asia Society/Institute for National Policy Research (INPR) - Taiwan Study Mission, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Taiwan's Role in the East Asian Economy: Implications for United States-Asia Relations Indonesia Briefing Book, 1996 July (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Taiwan's Role in the East Asian Economy: Implications for United States-Asia Relations Vietnam Briefing Book, 1996 June (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Articles regarding Taiwan, 1996 May-June (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Asia Society/Institute for National Policy Research (INPR) - Taiwan Study Mission, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Taiwan Study Mission Report - Drafts and revisions, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Doug Bereuter remarks at Williamsburg Conference of the Asia Society, 1996 April (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous materials regarding economic, legal, and government developments for China and Overseas Chinese, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Taiwan's Role in the East Asian Economy: Implications for the United States-Asia Relations Taiwan briefing materials, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Memos to Taiwan Study Mission members, 1996 August (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Articles, biographies, and briefing materials for Taiwan Study Mission meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Taiwan's Role in the East Asian Economy: Implications for United States-Asia Relations Hong Kong Briefing Book, 1996 July (Box 3, Frame 30-31)
  - Taiwan Study Mission - Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam visit, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Taiwan Study Mission - Taiwan Program, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Taiwan Study Mission - Vietnam Program, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Taiwan Study Mission - Indonesia Program, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Taiwan Study Mission - Hong Kong Program, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chicago Council on Foreign Relations Conference on American Foreign Policy in Asia - Taiwan and East Asia, by Harry Harding, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Taiwan's Role in the East Asian Economy: Implications for United States-Asia Relations Pre-Departure Briefings, 1996 May 22 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Taiwan's Role in the East Asian Economy: Implications for United States-Asia Relations Background Briefing Book, 1996 April (Box 4, Folder 39-41)
  - Master Roster for President of the National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (NCUSCR), 1998 March 20 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (NCUSCR) - President Search Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
  - Asia Pacific Philanthropy Consortium (APPC) International Conference consultancy appointment, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
  - National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (NCUSCR) Gala Dinners, 1993-1997 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Institute for EastWest Studies (IEWS) Vision Retreat, 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
  - Institute for EastWest Studies (IEWS), 1997 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA) - Trustees, 1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
  - Obor, the International Book Institute, Inc., 1996 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA), 1991-1997 (Box 5, Folder 54-57)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA) Finance Committee, 1994-1997 (Box 6, Folder 58-61)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA) Annual Meeting of Trustees, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 62-64)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (ICWA) Annual Meeting of Trustees, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 65-66)
  - Ford Foundation transition, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 67-69)
  - Ford Foundation - Program Division Transition Planning Meeting, 1996 May (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Okinawa as a Crossroads: Global Intellectual and Cultural Collaboration in the 21st Century Symposium Report, 1998 June (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Japan Center for International Exchange (JCIE) - Asia Pacific Agenda Project (APAP) Yokohama Forum reference papers, 1997 December (Box 7, Folder 72-73)
  - Report on Civil Society Resource Organizations (CSRO) and Development in Southeast Asia, 1998 May (Box 7, Folder 74-75)
  - Fourth Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) Roundtable: Regional Cooperation and Asian Recovery, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 76-78)
  - Workshop on the Central Economic Reform Issues Facing China - Salem, Massachusetts, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 79-80)
  - Global ThinkNet (GTN) Tokyo Conference, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Harvard Institute for International Development (HIID) Conference - China's Integration into the World Economy, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Workshop on Corporate Philanthropy in Vietnam, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - International Conference on Supporting the Nonprofit Sector in Asia - Bangkok, Thailand, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - International Conference on Supporting the Nonprofit Sector in Asia - Bangkok, Thailand, 1995-1997 (Box 8, Folder 85-87)
  - Japan-China Relations: New Voices Calling for a New Era conference, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Europe trip, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Beijing, China trip, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Tokyo, Japan trip, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Enhancing the Tripartite Relationship between China, the U.S., and Japan - Beijing Conference, 1996 December (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Japan Center for International Exchange (JCIE) Research Reports - Enhancing the Trilateral Relationship between China, the U.S., and Japan, 1997 June (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Japan Center for International Exchange (JCIE) Research Reports - The Future of the Asia-Pacific Region and Cooperation among China, the U.S., and Japan, 1997 June (Box 9, Folder 94-95)
  - China-U.S.-Japan Trilateral Project - Tokyo Workshop, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - China-U.S.-Japan Trilateral Project, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 97-98)
  - Japan Center for International Exchange (JCIE) - China-U.S.-Japan Trilateral Project, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Houston, Texas/Chicago, Illinois trip, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Papers for the First Asia-Pacific Public Affairs Forum (APPAF) Annual Conference, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Asia-Pacific Public Affairs Forum (APPAF) Annual Conference, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Asia-Pacific Public Affairs Forum (APPAF) Annual Conference, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - International Conference on Supporting the Nonprofit Sector in Asia - Seoul, Korea, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Taiwan trip, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - International Conference on Supporting the Nonprofit Sector in Asia - Manila, Philippines, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Council on Foundations Annual Conference - Hawaii, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Council on Foundations and philanthropy, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 108-109)
  - Asia Society - Atlanta, Georgia trip regarding Hong Kong transition, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - London, United Kingdom trip, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - New Delhi, India trip, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Council on Economic Priorities (CEP), 1997 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Hopkins-Nanjing Center for Chinese and American Studies, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Hopkins-Nanjing Council Meeting, 1998-2000 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX) 40th anniversary, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Centre for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS) review - Jakarta, Indonesia, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - China Association of Science Foundations (CASF) Workshop on Fund Management, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - U.S. Council for Security Cooperation in the Asia Pacific (USCSCAP) Board of Directors meeting, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Harvard University Asia Center - Asia Vision 21, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Harvard University Seminar, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Population Council Population and Development Review, 1999 January (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - International Workshop - China's Public Policy Choices into the Next Century, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 123-124)
  - Ford Foundation Beijing, China Office 10th anniversary, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Rye Radiology, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 126-127)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted – confidential material.
  - Clemente Holdings (Asia) Ltd. (CHA) Board of Directors Meeting, 1998 September 15 (Box 11, Folder 128-129)